嘿，你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, and welcome back to my OpenGL series
把它和布景混在一起了
mixing it up a little bit with the set
我的意思是上期
I mean last one
你们肯定注意到了
you guys were certainly noticing that
我只是我经常挥动我的手
I was just I wave my hands around a lot
我偶尔差点撞到那棵仙人掌
I was coming pretty close to hitting that cactus occasionally
并且我只是不想失去一只手
and that was just I don't want to lose a hand
所以总的说来就是我们把它混在一起了
so we're basically mixing it up
我们基本上改变了
we're basically changed
我想我要做一个微妙的改变
I thought I'd make a subtle kind of change
只是为了避免失去一只手的风险
just to get rid of that whole risk of losing a hand
我可不想反应过度之类的
I didn't want to overreact or anything like that
所以我稍微改变了一下布景
so I changed the set slightly
差不多把仙人掌处理掉了
kind of got rid of the cactus
不过它还在这个房间里, 但在很远的地方
it's still in this room, but it's all the way over there
不管怎样, 希望你们喜欢这种新形式
anyway, hope you guys like this new kind of format
这可能会更随意一些
it's gonna be a lot more casual
因为我不喜欢表现得很专业
because I'm not a big fan of being professional quite
跟你们说实话吧
to be quite frank with you guys
并且希望这只是
and hopefully this is just gonna be
会有一点
gonna be a little bit
对你们来说, 看起来和听起来也容易一些
a little bit easier for you guys to watch and listen to as well
不用像机器人一样把所有东西都看一遍
without kind of me going through everything like a robot
并且很快的, 结束了
and just quickly, kind of end up
每一个视频都要花一两个小时来制作
having to spend like an hour or two editing every single video
所以不管如何, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
so anyway, welcome back to my OpenGL series
上一次, 我们讨论了着色器
last time, we talked about shader stuff
并且事实上, 前两期, 我们讨论的都是着色器
and in fact, the last two episodes, we've been kind of talking about shader stuff
我们具体讨论了什么是着色器
specifically we talked about what shaders were
以及我们实际上不得不去写一个非常简单的顶点和片段着色器
and we actually had to go writing a very simple vertex and fragment shader
那基本上就是让我们的三角形变成了红色
that basically just made our triangle red
如果你们还没看过那一期
if you guys haven't seen that episode yeah
一定要点击这里去看看
definitely click up there
因为你需要看了那个视频才能看这个视频
because you need to watch that in order to get this video
因为这个视频将
because what this video is going to
将是关于
is going to be about
基本上就是上期的延伸
is just basically continuing on with that
并且更具体的是
and more specifically
我将向你们展示, 我喜欢如何处理着色器
I'm going to show you, how I like to deal with shaders
因为, 就像我们现在对代码所做的
because, kind of what we've been doing right now with the code
基本上就是, 我的意思是, 如果我们看一下上次的代码
is basically, I mean if we look at the code that we had last time
我们有这个创建着色器的函数
we have this function where we can compile a shader
然后我们创建了, 并且所有这些
and then we kind of created and all of that
但我们基本上还是不得不传入它
but we still have to basically take it in
好吧, 现在我们这儿最大的问题
well, the biggest problem here right now for us
就是我们还是需要把它(着色器)作为字符串传进去
is that we still need to take it in kind of as strings
这是一个问题, 因为, 好吧
that's a bit of an issue, because, well
首先, 看看这些字符串, 你可以看到
first of all, looking at these strings, you can see
我们不得不在每处添加换行符和引号
we have to add new line characters and quotes everywhere
在这一点上写着色器对我们来说不是很舒服
it's just not very comfortable for us to write shader at this point in it
很容易漏掉一个换行符或类似的东西
it's pretty easy to just miss a new line or something like that
并且最终得到的是一些漏洞
and end up with some kind of bug
而且我真的不想那样写
and I don't want to really do that
所以我们肯定会解决那个问题
so we're definitely going to fix that up
因此我们实际上可以专门从一个文件中传入我们的着色器
so that we can actually take our shaders in from a file as specifically
我看许多人都这么做的
what I see a lot of people doing
我的意思是, 这是完全合理的做法
which is I mean, completely reasonable
因为OpenGL确实在一定程度上加强了它
because OpenGL does kind of enforce it to a degree is that
实际上人们将创建两个不同的文件
what people will actually do is create two different files
一个是顶点着色器, 一个是片段着色器
one for the vertex shader, and one for the fragment shader
说实话, 我真的不喜欢那样
I'm really not a fan of that, to be honest
我的意思是有两个不同的文件就像那啥
I mean having two different files like why
我是说, 在某些情况下, 分散着色器会是有用的
I mean, in some cases, it can be useful to divide shaders up
比如, 你可能有个顶点着色器
for example, you might have a vertex shader
它只接收像一定数量的参数
which just takes in like a certain amount of parameters
一定数量的输入, 并且只输出位置
certain amount of inputs, and just outputs the position
并且它将提供一些数据给片段着色器
and that's it will provide some kind of data to the fragment shader
而它可能是一个非常简单的顶点着色器
and it might be a really simple vertex shader
例如, 你可以用三个不同的片段着色器配对它
which you can pair up with three different fragment shaders for example
并且在那种情况下, 你们可能会争论, 好了
and in that case, you might argue well, okay
你知道我正在载入这个文件
you know I'm loading this file
我不想必须把两个着色器绑在一起
I don't want to necessarily tie the two shaders together
比如把顶点一起放在片段着色器中
like the vertex in the fragment shader together
不一定想必须那么做
don't necessarily want to do that
这是一个争论
that's one argument
但我们已经有了同样的例子
but we've got a like
我们一会儿也会遇到那种情况
we'll deal with that as well in a minute here
但是, 重要的是, 我不喜欢必须, 就像
but, the big thing is that I don't like having to, like
为什么有两个不同的文件, 对吧
why have two different files, right
那并没有实际的原因
there's no actual reason for that
它其实有点烦人
it's actually a little bit annoying
你不得不创建两个不同的文件
you have to make two different files
你不得不从两个不同的文件读取
you have to read in two different files
当你编辑它们的时候
when you're editing them
你不得不, 就像
you have to, like
在两个文件之间切换, 或者把它们并排打开
switch between the two, or have them open the side by side
只是不太舒服
it's just not very comfortable
而我只是关心冲突, 就像
and I'm all about conflict, like
很明显我是坐在沙发上而不是椅子上, 和一张桌子
clearly I'm sitting on a couch here instead of a chair, and a table
所以我喜欢做的是将两个着色器合并到一个文件中, 明白吧
so what I like to do is combine the two shaders into one file, right
只有一个有顶点和片段着色器的文件
just have one file with a vertex and a fragment shader
当然, 在以后
and of course, in the future
如果你需要用到有一大堆片段着色器的一个顶点着色器
if you want to use one vertex shader with a bunch of fragment shaders
你仍可以那样做, 你仍然可以
you can still do that, you can still
因为很明显, 当我们最后给OpenGL着色器时
because obviously, when we give the shaders to OpenGL at the end
它们仍然需要有明确的划分, 对吧
they still need to have that clear division, right
我们不能简化到只给OpenGL一个, 就像
we can't just simply give OpenGL one, like
一串源码字符串, 然后它就可以处理它了
one string of source code, and then it can deal with it
它还是需要知道
it still needs to kind of know
它仍然需要那种区分在两者之间
it still needs to kind of have that distinction between
这是我的顶点着色器源码
this is my vertex shader source code
以及这是我的片段着色器源码
and this is my fragment shader source code
因此我们仍然会给它提供那些
and we're still going to provide it with that
这对我们有利
it's just on our side
基本上对于用户和程序一样的
basically as the user as the program
对开发人员写这样的代码也一样
as the developer writing this kind of code
我们将把它全部写在一个文件中
we're going to write it all in one file
而我马上就会告诉你, 我们是如何分成两个着色器的
and I'll show you how we divided into two shaders in a minute
这很像DirectX
this is very much like DirectX
你可能真的有点
you might actually kind of
在这个系列中
throughout this series
你将可能看到我特别喜欢引用Direct3D/11, 关于
you'll probably see me reference Direct3D 11 specifically quite a lot with
如何组织我的OpenGL代码
how I actually organized my OpenGL code
因为当你在处理游戏引擎时
because when you deal with game engines
你会使用多个接口, 多个图形接口
you'll be using multiple apis, multiple graphics apis
很可能是给它一个重要的引擎
most likely give it a serious engine
并且你可能会
and you kind of will probably
如果你的引擎支持Direct3D
if your engine supports Direct3D
或者即使它不支持, 你也会发现自己
or even if it doesn't, you'll probably find yourself
使OpenGL表现地更像DirectX
making OpenGL behave more like DirectX
因为DirectX是一个更好的api
because DirectX is just a better api
不管怎样, 让我们进入一些代码
anyway, let's get into some code
然后我将给你们展示, 这一切的原理
and I'll show you how all this is going to work
所以首先, 我们实际上要做的就是
so the first thing, we're actually going to do is just
创建一个包含这两个着色器的文件
create a file which contains these two shaders
以便我们了解
so that we know
我们实际上是如何处理它们的
how we're actually going to deal with them
所以, 这里, 在我的源目录中
so, over here, in my kind of source directory
实际上我将右键点击OpenGL
I'm actually going to right click on OpenGL
点击新建文件夹
hit add and then new folder
我们就叫这res, 就是放置资源的文件夹
we're going to call this res, which sets for resources
并且然后在那个res文件夹下
and then under that res folder
我实际上会创建另一个叫shaders的文件夹
I'm actually going to create another folder called shaders
而这是专门为了放着色器
and this is specifically going to be for shaders
在以后, 我们将会有像纹理之类的其他资源
we will have other resources like textures and stuff like that in the future
所以我要把所有这些都保持干净整洁
so I just want to keep all of this really nice and tidy
我们右键点击shaders, 点击添加新项
we'll right click on shaders, hit at new item
那么然后, 在这儿, 我添加一个文件
and then, here, I'm just going to add a file
现在, 这儿你点什么都没关系
now, doesn't matter what you click here
因为我们会改变扩展名
because we're kind of going to change the extension
不论如何, 我们就叫这个为Shader.shader
anyway, we're just going to call this Shader.shader
或者实际上我们可以把它重命名为
or specifically we might rename this to something like
好吧, 我不知道, 它只是让那个三角形变成红色的
well, I don't know, it just makes that triangle red
我们就叫它Basic.shader吧
we're just gonna call it Basic.shader
因为这就像我们处理的基本着色器
because this is just going to be like our basic shader that we deal with
点击添加, 那么现在我们有了一个着色器文本
I'm gonna hit add, and now we have a shader
你可以看到它没有显示c++图标
you can see that it's not showing up as like the c++ icon
这非常重要
which is very important
我们不想意外地把它编译成c++代码
we don't want to accidentally compile this as c++ code
因为当然它不能编译
because of course it won't compile
让我们返回Application.cpp文件
let's go back to Application.cpp
我来复制这整块代码
I'm going to copy this entire kind of block of code
并且我需要把它粘贴到这个文件
and I want to paste it into this file
现在我们需要清理一下
now we need to clean this up a little bit
特别是, 我要把这两个字符串都去掉
specifically I'm going to get rid of the string, of course from both of these
在这儿, 然后实际上去掉这个
here, and then to actually clean this up
我们可以一行一行地看
we could go through this kind of line by line
这有点难
it's going to be a bit hard
所以我要给你们展示一个小技巧
so I'll show you guys a bit of a trick
如果你按ctrl+h
if you hit ctrl h
这将打开查找和替换对话框
that will bring up the find and replace dialog
你们可以在这里看到
which you can see over here
我们将抓取引号, 然后将它们替换为空
we're going to grab quotes and replace them with nothing
如果你按alt+a
if you hit alt a
或者我觉得这里有个可替换的按钮
or I think there's a replaceable button here
alt+a, 我们就可以删除所有那些了
alt a, we'll get rid of all that
并且然后, 最后, 我们还想去掉换行符
and then, finally we want to get rid of the new lines as well
所以我也要把 替换成空, alt+a
so I'll also replace backslap n with nothing, alt a
好了, 我们继续
done, and there we go
你可以看到那有多简单
you can see how much easier that was
然后, 浏览一下这个代码
then kind of just going through this code
手动清理所有东西
cleaning everything up manually
太好了, 我们搞定了
okay, fantastic, we've got this
很难区分顶点着色器和片段着色器
kind of hard to tell the distinction between a vertex and a fragment shader
所以我喜欢做的就是
so what I like to do
你只需要来到这最上面
you just come up here at the top
然后我会输入 #shader vertex, 了解了吧
and I'm going to hit hash shader and then vertex, okay
然后我要复制它
and then I'm going to copy that
并且就在片段着色器的上方, 叫这fragment吧
and just above the fragment shader, call this fragment
所以当我们有了所有不同的着色器
so when we have all of our different shaders
我们可能有其他的着色器类型, 比如细分曲面着色器
we might have other shader types, like tessellation shaders
或者像那个几何着色器之类的一些着色器
or something like that geometry shaders
诸如此类的东西
that kind of stuff
我们也可以为它添加一个节点
we can also probably add a section for that
但是对于现在
but for now
你可以看到, 我已经很清楚地把它分成了片段着色器和顶点着色器
you can see that I've clearly kind of divided this into my fragment shader and my vertex shader
不用太担心这里的语法高亮显示
don't worry too much about the syntax highlighting here
因为我们实际上已经指定了不太明显的着色器扩展
because we have actually specified the dull shader extension
VS可能会尝试突出显示它, 好像它是
visual studio probably going to try and highlight this as if it was a
大提琴, 听起来像DirectX类型的着色器
cello, sounds like a DirectX kind of shader
不管怎样, 那对我们还是有帮助的
but anyway, that's still kind of sort of helpful for us
因为它高亮了一些事情, 就像数字
because it highlights some things like numbers
这让它看起来更容易一些, 但是你可以看到
and kind of makes that easier to see, but you can see
这是我布局着色器的策略
this is kind of my strategy for laying out shader
它很容易
it's very easy
你可以同时看到发生了什么
you can see what's going on all at once
你不需要在两个不同的文件之间切换
you don't need to flip between two different files
并且它真的很好, 很简单, 干净, 有条理
and it's just yeah it's just really nice and easy, and clean, and organized
所以让我们回到我们的应用
so let's go back to our application
我现在要移除这整块代码
I'm going to get rid of this entire block here now
现在, 为了理解这里发生了什么
now to kind of understand what's going on here
我们有CreateShader函数
we have our CreateShader function
它接收两个源码字符串
which takes in the two strings of source code
我们仍然需要为它提供两个不同的源码字符串
we still need to provide it with two different strings of source code
所以现在我们的计划就是读取这个文件
so now really our plan is just to take this file
然后把它分成两块字符串, 对吧, 分成两个字符串
and divide it up into two blocks of strings, right, into two strings
一个是我们的片段着色器源码
our fragment shader source code
而另一个就是我们的顶点着色器源码
and our vertex shader source code
让我们回到应用做那个吧
let's go back to application and do that
我要向上滚动到这里, 向上滚动到最顶端
I'm going to scroll up here, up here to the very top
尽量让这个函数在上面, 为什么不呢, static
more to try this function at the top, why not, static
我们现在就让它返回void
we'll make it void for now
然后我们就叫它ParseShader
and we'll call this ParseShader
并且然后我们只让这个接收一个 const std::string&
and then I'm going to just make this take in a const std string
而这个将是我们的文件
and this will be a our file
我可能会叫这个filePath
I might call this file path
而我们实际上去读取这个的方式就是, 当然
and the way that we're actually going to read this in is, of course
首先, 我们需要去打开一个文件
first of all, we need to open a file
并且我会使用一种现代c++的方式来实现这个
and I'm going to do this in a bit of like a c++ modern c++ way
不一定是我个人在游戏引擎中读取文件的方式
not necessarily the way that I would personally read files in a game engine
因为C++往往比C那种文件接口慢一点, 但是
because c++ tends to be a little bit slower than the c kind of file api, but
因为这个系列显然是关于OpenGL的
because this series is obviously just about OpenGL
我需要写一些代码
I want to kind of write codes
它是那种更容易阅读, 更安全, 所有这些
that's a lot easier to read and a lot safer and all of that
所以我将基本上包括一个叫做fstream的库
so I'm just going to basically include something called fstream
它表示文件流
which says for file stream
并且然后在这里, 我会写 std::ifstream
and then over here, I'm going to write std ifstream
我们就叫它stream
we'll just call it stream
这从输入文件流开始
this starts for input file stream
而然后我会给它那个filePath
and then I'll kind of give it that filePath
那是我们尝试在这儿打开的实际文件
that's the actual file that we're trying to open here
那已经打开了这个文件
that already opens the file
所以现在我们需要做的就是一行一行地浏览那个文件
so now what we need to do is actually go through that file line by line
然后只去检查, 嘿
and just check to see, hey
这是我们指定地那个着色器类型吗
are we specifying a certain shader type
因为我们只添加我们自己的句法规则, 对吧
because we've kind of added our own syntax, right
我们在这里得到这个#shader vertex
we've got this hash shader vertex thing here
基本上就是说, 嘿
which basically says hey
这是一个新着色器节点
this is a new shader section
并且这就是那个着色器的类型
and this is the type of the shader that it is
所以我们需要去读取那个
so we need to kind of read in that
然后我们会一行一行的浏览这个文件
and we're going to go through the file line by line
并且我们实现那个的方法就是, 我们实际上会去循环 stream
and the way we'll do that is we'll actually do while stream
我们会使用一个叫getLine的函数, 所以就是
we'll use a function called getLine, so while getLine stream
然后我们会在这里创建一个叫做line的流
and then we'll make a stream here called line
它将会包含我们实际的数据行
which will contain our actual line
那基本上不会等于0
while that doesn't equal zero basically
现在getLine是一个在string.h中的函数
now getLine is a function that actually is inside the string header
所以我们需要包含string.h
so we need to include string
所以当getLine仍然是有效的
so while getLine is still kind of valid
这意味着文件中还有更多的数据行要读
which means there are still more lines for us to read inside the file
我们要做的基本上就是查看数据行或查找
we're going to just basically check to see line or find
实际的行是否包含我们的着色器在这里自定义句法结构的标记
if that actual line contains our shader on a custom syntax token here
并且如果那个不等于std::string::npos
and if that doesn't equal std string npos
基本上是一个无效的字符串位置
which is basically an invalid string position
因为find会返回给我们实际的字符串位置
because find will return us to the actual string position
你可以看到它返回一个size_t
you can see it returns a size_t
它不返回布尔值或类似的东西
it doesn't return a boolean or anything like that
不管它是否找到了我们的字符串
whether or not it actually found our string
它实际上只是返回给我们它的位置
it actually just returns to us the position of it
所以如果结果是正的, 说明它没有
so if it's end positive, means it doesn't
它没有找到字符串
it hasn't found it
所以如果它在这个数据行上找到了着色器
so if it has found shader on that line
基本上我们需要找到
we need to basically find
它是哪个着色器类型
which type of shader it is
再一次, 我只使用line.find()
and again, I'm just going to use line  find
如果它是一个顶点, 如果它找到一个vertex
if it's going to be vertex, if it finds vertex
然后基本上我们需要设置模式为顶点
then we're going to basically have to set the kind of mode to vertex
这是我们马上就要做的
which we'll do in a minute
并且在另一个方面
and otherwise though
如果它找到了fragment
if it finds fragment
如果它不等于std::string::npos
so if that doesn't equal std string npos
然后我们将把模式设置为fragment
then we're going to set the mode to fragment
好了, 所以这就是它的工作原理
okay, so that's kind of how this is going to work
我们只需要一行一行地浏览
we're just going to go through a line by line
并且我们也会继续添加顶点
and we're going to keep adding vertex well
如果类型设置为顶点, 我们会继续添加这些数据行
if the type is set to vertex, we're going to keep adding these lines
基本上就是添加到我们的顶点着色器
basically to our vertex shader string
如果是片段, 我们会把它们添加到片段着色器字符串中
if it's fragment, we're going to add them to the fragment shader string
非常简单
pretty simple
所以现在我们实际上需要添加这些字符串
so now we actually need to add the strings
所以我们从这些数据行中读取出来的
so we're reading out these lines
就是我们在写入某种缓冲
that we're reading into some kind of buffer
我们可以一行行地堆在一起
where we can just pile on line by line
就是顶点着色器和片段着色器
what the vertex shader the fragment shader is
所以要做到这一点
so to do that
我会使用到叫字符串流的东西
I'm going to use something called string stream
所以我们不得不包含那个
so we'll have to include that
那么那就是#include sstream
and that'll be on the include sstream
如果我们向下滚动到这儿
if we scroll down here
我就创建两个不同的字符串流
I'm just going to make two different string streams
那么我们就叫它ss, 然后我实际上就会使用
so we'll call this ss ,and I'm actually just gonna use
从栈上分配两个在这儿
a kind of stack allocated right here to have two of them
一个是为了顶点着色器
one of them's going to be for the vertex shader
当然另一个就是为了片段着色器
of course one of them's going to be for the fragment shader
并且这个想法是
and the idea is
我们也需要某种模式
we need to have some kind of mode as well
所以我们现在是在读入一个顶点着色器或片段着色器
so are we currently reading in a vertex shader or a fragment shader
为了做到那个
to do that
我就要在这儿创建一个enum类, 叫做ShaderType
I'm just going to create an enum class here called ShaderType
然后我们有一个NONE, 也就是- 1
and then we're gonna to have none which is negative one
然后当然我们有一个VERTEX
then we're going to have a vertex of course
就是0, 以及FRAGMENT就是1
which is zero, and fragment which is one
我是显示指定数字的
i'm being very explicit with these numbers
并且马上我会告诉你们为什么
and i'll tell you why in a minute
我们还会存储我们正在当前读入的着色器类型
we're also going to store the current shader type that we're reading in
所以我会把这个(type)默认设置为ShaderType::NULL
so we'll set this equel to null by default
好了, 酷, 所以
okay, cool, so
如果我们找到了vertex, 如果我们在一数据行上找到了顶点着色器
if we find vertex, if we find shader of vertex on a line
我们需要把模式或类型实际上设置为ShaderType::VERTEX
we need to set the mode or the type to actually be shader of type vertex
当然, 对于fragment, 我会把它设置为ShaderType::FRAGMENT
and then of course, for fragment, we can set it equal to fragment
我只是随便设置一下
I'm kind of setting this up loosely
我的代码可能会更干净一点
I could be a little bit cleaner with my code
以及实际上有更多的函数, 就像
and actually have some more functions and stuff like that
为了计算出一个字符串中的类型是什么
to work out what the type is from a string
但再说一次, 说实话, 这是一个非常简单的函数
but again,it's stoical, this is a really simple function
所以当我完成了那个
so once I've done that
如果我, 如果我们在一数据行上看见了#shader
if I kind of, if we see hash shader on a line
我们就知道我们需要去设置一个类型
we know that we need to set a type
否则, 如果它是其他的代码行
otherwise, if it's any other kind of line of code
然后我们实际上就需要
then we actually need to
把它添加到顶点或片段的着色器源码中
add it to either the vertex or the fragment shader source code
并且我们实现那个的方法就是
and the way we do that is
使用字符串流
to the string stream
让我把这个多余的空格删掉吧
let me just get rid of this extra space
对于字符串流
to the string stream
我基本上就是把数据行推到它里面去
I'm going to basically push the line into it
现在我也需要知道把哪个数据行推进去
now I need to know which one to push too
而那就是为什么我们需要得到着色器类型
and that's why we've got the shader type
所以我要拿到这个type, 并且直接把它转换成一个整型
so I'm going to grab the type and just cast it to an int
然后把它作为这个数组的一个索引使用
and use it as an index into this array
我们知道这个数组有两个元素
we know that the array contains two elements
并且我们知道, 基本上, 那个数组的第一个元素会是顶点着色器
and we know that basically the first element in that array is going to be vertex
而第二个元素就是片段着色器
and the second one is going to be fragment
所以我在这里使用了数组
so I'm kind of using arrays here
这是一种比较小机灵的方式, 实际上为了
in a little bit of a clever way to actually
你知道的, 自动化程度更高一点
you know automate this a little bit more
所以我不必有分支结构
so I don't have to have a branch
我基本上就是说
where I basically say
如果这个类型是
if the type is
你知道的顶点着色器, 就把它添加到顶点着色器字符串流
you know vertex, add it to the vertex string stream
如果这个类型是片段着色器
if the type is fragment
就把它添加到片段着色器字符串流
add it to the fragment string stream
我可以用这个类型作为数组的索引
I can kind of just use the type as an index into the array
这基本上会好一点
which is just going to be a little bit better basically
所以在这里, 我基本上就是添加这个数据行到那个字符串流
so over here I'm going to basically add line into that string stream
后面补充一个换行符
followed by a new line character
就这样, 差不多就是这样
just like that, and that's pretty much it
我的意思是如果你看看这个代码
I mean if you look at this code
这个应该把我们的着色器分离到两个不同的类型
this should divide our shader into two different types
然后把它们添加到对应的字符串流
and add them to the appropriate string stream
所以最后, 在结尾这里
so finally, at the end here
我实际上需要返回我的代码
I need to actually return my code
现在我们有一个小问题
now we have a little bit of an issue
因为我们在尝试返回两个字符串, 并且当然
because we are trying to return two strings, and of course
你可以只返回一个
you can only return one
你可以在c++中返回一个变量
kind of you can return one variable in c++
所以我们如何返回两个变量
so how do we return two variables
现在我们可以使用一个叫做元组或对组的东西
now we could use something called a tuple or a pair
事实上我对此有很多感觉
I actually have a lot of feelings about that
实际上, 我这周也许可能制作了一期c++的视频
actually I might make a c++ video this week maybe
那实际上是专门处理这种多个返回类型的事情
that actually deals with this kind of multiple return type thing specifically
我认为我会
I think I will
实际上那可能是个不错的主意
actually that's probably a good idea
但我不太喜欢用那种东西
I don't like using that stuff
并且我会在c++系列视频中解释原因
and I'll explain why in the c++ video
我不想让你们在这儿感到无聊
I don't want to bore you guys here
但是我会怎么做
but what I would do
如果我需要在这里返回多个类型, 就是
if I need to kind of return multiple types here is
我实际上会创建一个叫Shader的结构体
I would actually make a struct called shader
不知道, ShaderSources, 或之类的一些名字吧
I don't know, shader sources, or something like that
我们实际上可能会叫它ShaderProgramSource
we might actually just call this shader program source
并且实际上这是包含我们的
and this is actually going to contain our
我们就叫它VertexSource
we'll call this vertex source
我有点喜欢首字母大写
I kind of like to capitalize a bit
我几乎把这当成了c#的属性
I'm kind of treating this almost like a c# property
那就是为什么我把这个首字母大写
that's why I'm capitalizing this
因为它们在公开的领域
because they are just public fields
所以我们就取VertexSource和FragmentSource
so we're taking vertex source and fragment source
好的, 很酷, 非常基本的结构体
okay, cool, very basic struct
那么我就返回那个结构体
and I'm going to just return that struct
并且然后在我的函数的结尾这里
and then at the end here of my function
当我有了这两个
once I have the two
当我已经构建完了
once I've built up
以及我已经读取了该文件中的所有源码
and I've read all of the source code from that file
我就返回
I'm just going to return
基本上是一个结构体, 就这个结构体, 对吧
basically a struct, that this struct, right
所以我把VertexSource设置为ss[0].str()
so I'm going to set the vertex source to be ss zero dot str
那么然后就是ss[1].str(), 好了
and then ss one dot str, ok
这(.str())会给我们从字符串流返回的字符串
which gives us the string back from the string stream
而那就是我们现在需要做的一切
and that's all we need to do right now
所以这个代码应该给我们设置好了实际的着色器源码
so this code should set us up with the actual shader source code
对于顶点和片段着色器
for both the vertex and the fragment shader
漂亮
awesome
所以现在, 让我们向下滚动, 实际测试一下
so now, let's scroll down, and actually test this out
所以我将做的第一件事就是, 我会
so the first thing I'll do is, I'll kind of
我们可能要删除我们的shader
we might just get rid of our shader
至于现在, 就注释它好了
for now, just by commenting it out
说实话, 我只是想先看看我的函数是否起作用
I just really want to see if my function works first, to be honest
所以我们输入ShaderProgramSource source, 或之类的东西
so we'll go shader program source source or something like that
等于ParseShader()
equals ParseShader
而然后我们传入我们的文件路径
and then we'll take in our file path
这就是res/Shaders/Basic.shader
which is just going to be res/Shaders/Basic.shader
这是我们的文件
which is our file
那么res/Shader/Basic.shader
so res slash shaders slash basic dot shader
现在这是我们的第一个例子
now this is kind of the first instance of us
实际上在c++中读取一个文件
actually reading a file in c++
在这个系列中使用我的方式
in the series on my channel
所以基本上你需要知道的是
so basically what you need to know about this is that
如果你像那样指定一个相对路径
if you specify a relative path like that
而不是一个绝对路径之类的一些东西
so not something that is an absolute path
你知道像c:\users, 无论什么
you know like c:\users, whatever
从c驱动开始的, 不管什么
starting from the c drivers, whatever
由于我们指定了一个相对路径
since we're specifying a relative path
相对部分始终来自工作目录
relative parts are always from the working directory
现在, 如果你在VS之外运行可执行文件
now if you run the executable outside of virtual studio
这个默认的工作目录就会使
the default working directory is just going to be the
包含那个可执行文件的目录
directory that contains that executable
所以一切都会相对于那个
so everything will be relative to that
但是如果我们通过这个VS的调试器运行这个的话
but if we're running this through the visual studio debugger
这个工作目录实际上就会设置成
the working directory is actually set
我们VS调试器的那种属性
by our visual studio debugging kind of property
所以如果我们右键打开这个OpenGL项目
so if we right click on open on the OpenGL project
点击属性
hit properties
你可以看到, 我们有一个叫做调试的选项卡在那儿
you can see, over here we have a tab called debugging
对吧, 而在下面, 我们有个工作目录
right, and under here, we have a working directory
你们可以看到这儿默认设置成了我们的项目目录, 所以
you can see here that is set by default to our project directory, so
我们知道这个文件是相对于我们项目目录的
we know that this file is relative to the project directory
那就是这个目录
that is the directory
实际上包含我们的项目文件
that actually contains our project file
在这个情况下就是
which in this case is
有我们vcxproj的这个目录
this directory which just has our vcxproj
所以你们可以看到它应该相对这个目录
so you can see it should be relative to this
就是res/Shader
so res slash shader
/Basic.shader
slash Basic dot shader
并且那正是我刚在这里写的
and that's exactly what I've written over here
既然我们已经得到了这个, 实际上那我们就写, std::cout << source.VertexSource
now that we've got this, let's actually just std cout source VertexSource
并且我也会对FragmentSource做同样的处理
and also I'll do the same for FragmentSource
现在为了把这个用某种方式区分以下
now to divide this in some way
让它看起来更清楚一些
just to make it extra clear
我也会在这儿复制两次这个, 并且写上
I'm also going to copy this kind of twice here, and write
你知道像那样的VERTEX
you know VERTEX like that
以及FRAGMENT, 因此我们真就可以看到
and FRAGMENT, so that we can really see
我们有两个不同的着色器
the two different shader we have
那么我就按f5, 好了
and I'm just gonna hit f5, okay
我这里还有一个语法错误
I've got one more syntax error here
当我们这样布局着色器时
when we do GL to lay shader
顺便说一下, 来自上一期的这个代码是错的
by the way, this code was wrong from the last episode
我添加了一点东西
I added a little thing
有点像是在第一次的时候
kind of just in permeate prime
像时在我的视频编辑软件中
like in my video editing software
我只添加了一点小注释
I just add a little kind of note
就像这个函数应该是
being like this is what the function should be
它应该不是
it should not be
glDeleteShader, 我不知道为什么会写那个
glDeleteShader, don't know why I wrote that
它应该是glDeleteProgram
it should be glDeleteProgram
好了, 因为着色器实际上只是一个着色器类型
okay, because shader is actually just one shader type
我们的程序实际上会被删除, 我们的程序
our program is to actually go to delete, our programs
应该是这样的
that's what it should be
让我们取消那个的注释吧, 因为我们已经
let's comment that out for now though, because we did
得到了那个着色器代码
kind of come out that shader code
让我们按f5去运行这个程序
let's hit f5 to run this program
希望我们可以看到我们的解析运行正常
hopefully we can see our parsing working correctly
所以当我来到我的控制台
so if I go to my console
你应该可以看到, 我们有
you should see that we have
VERTEX, 然后就是顶点着色器, 接着FRAGMENT
VERTEX, and then the vertex shader, and FRAGMENT
然后就说片段着色器
and then the fragment shader
所以这看起来不错
so it looks pretty good to me
它们看起来都是正确的着色器
they look like there are correct shader
没有崩溃之类的事
nothing crash or anything like that
我觉得很完美
looks pretty perfect to me
让我们继续, 并实际导入到我们的源代码
let's go ahead and actually pipe that into our source code
特别是在我们的着色器编译函数中
was specifically into our shader compilation function
所以我把这个还原回来
so I'll bring this back
并且我也将我的glDeleteProgram还原回来
and I'll bring back my glDeleteProgram as well
而不是提供顶点着色器和片段着色器
and then instead of kind of providing vertex shader and fragment shader
现在我们有了这个
now we've got this
我们只提供source.vertexSource和source.fragmentSource
we can just provide source.vertexSource and source.fragmentSource
就那样吧, 让我们按f5
just like that, let's hit f5
然后你就可以看到, 我们得到了一个红色的三角形
and you can see that we get a red triangle
如果我返回我的Basic.shader文件
if I go back to my Basic.shader file
让我们直接去改变它, 让我们使它
let's go ahead and change it, let's make it
不知道, 让我们把它做成一个漂亮的蓝色
I don't know, let's just make it a nice little blue
所以, 我就改成0.2
so I'll make a zero point two
0.3, 0.8, 那么然后按f5
zero point three, zero point eight, and then hit f5
正如你所看到的, 我们得到了一个漂亮的蓝色三角形
as you can see, we got a nice blue triangle
太棒了, 所以我希望你们喜欢这个视频
awesome, so I hope you guys enjoyed this video
我们基本上只是利用了着色器
we basically just took what we had with shaders
让它变得更好一点
made it a little bit better
将所有内容合并到一个文件中
combined it all into one file
并且现在我们可以在文件中创建着色器
and now we can create shader from files
这会更酷和更容易一些
which is pretty cool and gonna be way more easier
对我们来说, 这样做会容易得多
it's gonna be way easier for us to actually do that
随着我们现在继续这个系列的学习
as we progress on with this series now
以后, 我们会把这一切抽象到一个类中
in the future, we will probably abstract all this into a class
随着基于持续绘图的代码
as the code based kind of keeps drawing
现在, 我们不用担心它
for now, we're not gonna worry about it
我们要继续前进
we're just gonna move on
我们会讲顶点缓冲区和着色器
we've covered vertex buffers and shaders
这就是我确实想讲的下一期
the next step that I really want to cover
会是关于顶点缓冲区
is going to be about index buffers
好了, 因为我们需要一种方法实际去渲染我们的三角形
okay, because we need a way to actually render our triangle
就是使用一个叫索引缓冲区的东西
using something called an index buffer
并且我们会讲关于
and we'll talk about
为什么我们想要其中的一个, 这实际上是什么
why we want one of those, what that actually is
以及之类的一切, 在下一期视频
and all of that in the next video
因为它可能没有那么明显
because it's probably not that apparent
对于三角形来说, 它的必要性可能并不那么明显
the need for it probably isn't that apparent with a triangle
但是当我们得到更复杂的有价值的几何结构时
but as we kind of get more complex value geometry
我的意思是, 即使我们尝试渲染一个非常复杂的正方形, 对吧
I mean, even if we try and render a square which is pretty complex, right
这对我们有好处
it's gonna benefit us
对我们来说, 使用索引缓冲区将是一个巨大的好处
it's gonna be a huge benefit for us to use something called an index buffer
不管怎样, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你喜欢的话, 你可以点击这个点赞按钮
if you did, you can hit the like button
你可以通过访问patreon来帮助支持本系列
you can help support this series by going over to patron comfortable
对于这种方式
for such the channel
这儿有一些很酷的奖励
there are some pretty cool rewards
我是说我不会说谎
I mean I'm not gonna lie
我不会骗你们的, 对吧
I would never lie to you guys, right
首先, 这一系列将是毫无意义的
first of all, this series will be absolutely nothing
没有我patreon上的这些支持者
without my patreon supporters
那肯定没门
there's no way
我坐在这里
that I would be sitting here
在沙发上花这么多时间为你们制作视频
on a couch spending this much time making videos for you guys
除非我得到了支持, 所以这就是
unless I was getting the support, so this is
首先非常感谢你们让我这么做
thank you so much for letting me do this first of all
其次
the second of all
你会很早收到视频
you'll get videos early
你将获得所有源码
you'll get access to all the source code
这个系列, 一期接一期的
kind of episode by episode for this series
并且确实是我这个系列的所有源码
and really for all of my series
还有一件很酷的事情, 基本上就是
and there's this really cool thing where basically
如果你是置顶的支持者
if you're a top tier kind of supporter
这是我们每月一次的聚会
this is hang out that we do once a month
我们基本上是所有的支持者都参与其中
we're basically all the supporters get into one
就像是在discord上的视频聊天
like video chat thing on discord
并且我们只讨论
and we just talk about
我们只是聚会一个小时
we just hang out for an hour
基本上讨论一切东西
basically just talk about whatever
这真愉快, 一定要报名参加
it's a really good time, definitely sign up for that
如果你们对帮助支持系列感兴趣
if you're interested in help support a series
discord也是谈论这些东西的好地方
discord is also a really good place to talk about this stuff
而不仅仅是在下面留下评论
rather than just leaving a comment below
你也可以那样做
which you could do as well
当然, 我会尽量回复我的所有评论
of course, I try and respond to all my comments
你也可以直接去discord.com, 抱歉, 是TheCherno.com/discour
you can also head on over to discord com, sorry TheCherno com slash discord
那儿基本上就是个社区
where there's basically just a community
人们喜欢即时消息这种形式
people like an instant messaging kind of format
多频道的事情, 我们可以谈谈
thing with multiple channels, we can talk about
这个三角形, 这个OpenGL系列
this triangle,the OpenGL series
C++, 不管你想谈论什么
c++, whatever it is that you want to talk about
那里也有很多人
a lot of people there as well
可以帮你解决所有的问题
that can help you out with all your problems
当然, 别忘了在Twitter和Instagram上关注我
and of course, don't forget to follow me on Twitter and on Instagram
还有这个频道的会议
the conference at the channel as well
推广一切东西
just plugging absolutely everything
你也可以在这里买货物的
also you can buy the merch at this
我开玩笑的, 我还没有那个链接
I'm kidding, I don't have that link yet
但我一定会告诉你的
but I'll get back to you with that surely
下次索引缓冲区就出来了, 再见
and next time index buffers channel out, goodbye